是, 大臣  圣诞特别篇
THE LAST FANTASY | TLF HALFCD TeaM
压制：beiming6@TLF  字幕：破烂熊
仅供交流  严禁商用
-=破烂熊字幕组=-
翻译&校对&调轴: tpring
党派之戏
伯纳 有急事吗?我得批完这些国防部报告
Bernard, is it important? I must finish these Defence papers.
恐怕这事更紧急 大臣      什么事?
This is more urgent, Minister. What is it?
您的圣诞卡 大臣 不能再拖了
Your Christmas cards can't be postponed any longer.
要怎么签?      都标明了 大臣
Eugh. Which is which? They're labelled.
这些签吉姆 这些签吉姆哈克
These you sign Jim; these Jim Hacker
这些签吉姆和安妮 这些签安妮与吉姆哈克
these Jim and Annie; these Annie and Jim Hacker;
这些签爱你的安妮和吉姆      这些呢?
these Love from Annie and Jim. And those?
这些是印好的 不用签 只要过目一下
those have cyclostyled signatures so you needn't write anything.
检查有没有哪些需要亲笔签吉姆或吉姆哈克
Make sure none of them should have been personally signed Jim
或吉姆和安妮或安妮与吉姆哈克
or Jim and Annie or Annie and Jim Hacker
或爱你的安妮和吉姆
or Love from Annie and Jim.
那些呢?      那是给选民的
What about those? Constituency cards
您的竞选代理早上送来的
Your agent left them.
您看它们也分好了 这些签吉姆
As you see, they've been divided up. Those you sign Jim;
这些签吉姆哈克 这些...
those Jim Hacker; those Jim and...
多谢 伯纳 我明白了
Thank you, Bernard! I think I've got the gist.
就这些吗?      政党总部还有
Is that it? Apart from the ones at Party headquarters.
政党总部?去年我可没签
Party HQ? I didn't do those last year.
去年您不是党主席
You weren't Party Chairman last year.
唉 这张非寄不可吗?
Oh. Do I have to send this one?
怎么?      给莫里斯 欧共体的
Why not? It's to Maurice in Brussels.
就是他硬要推行欧洲香肠标准化计划
He forced through the plan to standardise the Euro sausage.
欧洲香肠?
Euro sausage?
明年咱们就得跟老英国香肠说再见
Next year we'll be waving goodbye to British sausage,
被迫引进那些外国垃圾
forced to accept some foreign muck
意大利蒜肠 德国泥肠之类
like salami or bratwurst or something.
他们不能不让我们吃英国香肠啊
They can't stop us eating the British sausage!
他们不让我们叫它香肠
It'll be called the
改叫"乳化高脂杂碎筒"
emulsified high-fat offal tube!
您就吞下去啦?
And you swallowed it?
我有责任推行欧共体政策嘛 这下我算毁了
It's my job to implement EEC regulations.
干吗跟我们的香肠过不去?      你不读报吗?
What they got against our sausage? Don't you ever read the papers?
我瞟了一眼 大臣 没能读下去
I glanced at it, but it rather put me off.
显然 他们嫌里面肉不够
Apparently, there's not enough meat in it.
"常规英国香肠含有32.5%脂肪 6.5%猪皮"
"The average British sausage consists of 32.5% fat, 6.5% rind,
"20%清水 10%面包干"
"20% water, 10% rusk
"5%调料 色素和防腐剂"
5% seasoning, preservative and colouring
"仅含有26%肉类"
"and only 26% meat,
"主要包括软骨 头部 下脚料"
"which is mostly gristle, head meat, other offcuts
"以及机械脱骨肉渣"
"and mechanically-recovered meat...
"以蒸汽从畜体上剥离"
"...steamed off the carcasses."
我觉得有点...我今天...
I don't feel particularly... I had one...
我今天早餐吃了一根
I had one for breakfast.
也许欧共体专员说得对
Perhaps the EEC commissioner is right.
就算对 选民也不爱听
He may be, but it'll be extremely unpopular with the voters.
算了 我们只好决不松口 反咬回去
We shall just have to grit our teeth and bite on the bullet.
如果您不松口 就没法反咬回去 因为...
You can't bite a bullet when gritting your teeth If you do that...
对不起
Sorry.
对了伯纳 你得告诉我
By the way, you were going to advise me
给助理办公室送什么礼物
what presents to get for the private office.
随您便 大臣 助理秘书送雪利酒
That's up to you. Bottles of sherry for the assistant secretaries,
日程秘书和通信秘书送大盒薄荷糖
large boxes of mints for the diary secretary
其余人送小盒薄荷糖
and small boxes of mints for the rest.
我的私人秘书呢?      哦 那是我
What about my Personal Private Secretary? That's me.
啊 对 我要送你什么?      您不用送我东西
Ah, yes, of course You don't have to give me anything.
我知道 伯纳 可我乐意送      哦 大臣
I know, but I'd like to. Oh, Minister...
随便 什么都行      比方说?
Well, anything, really. Such as?
这个 我比较喜欢惊喜
Well, really I would like a surprise.
要给你什么惊喜?
What sort of surprise should I give you?
按惯例 一瓶香槟酒就很惊喜
A bottle of champagne is the customary surprise.
我几点和汉弗莱开会?      这个取消了 大臣
What time is my meeting with Humphrey? That's been cancelled.
汉弗莱爵士和内阁秘书有个紧急会议
Sir Humphrey had an urgent meeting with the Cabinet Secretary.
内阁秘书 总让我紧张
The Cabinet Secretary. Always makes me feel rather nervous.
可以说 阿诺德爵士是全国最有权力的人
Sir Arnold is the most powerful chap in the country.
首相常任秘书 控制内阁议程 一切尽在掌握
controls Cabinet agenda, controls access to everything.
他有什么事?
I wonder what he's up to?
对了 汉弗莱      什么?
By the way, Humphrey... Yes?
我决定提前退休
I've decided to retire early.
真的 阿诺德?
Oh! Have you, Arnold?
就定在新年
In the New Year.
啊
Ah...
我的接班人面对政治家得立场坚定
My successor has to be firm with our political masters.
当然 这一点不能含糊
Absolutely. No nonsense with that lot!
还得讲策略      可不是
But tactful... Exactly.
温和 迷人 老练...      尤其要可靠
Suave, charming, emollient... And above all, sound.
可靠? 对了 可靠
Sound? Oh, yes, sound.
因此 我有责任为首相举荐
So my duty is to convey a recommendation to the Prime Minister
全面符合这些条件的常任秘书
the Permanent Secretaries best meets these stringent criteria.
那么 这个...
And, er...
你...这个...现在有没有...
...Have you, er... Er, er, is there, er... Does anyone, er...
你看 这行的真谛不在于找对答案
You see, in this job, the problem isn't really finding the answers
而在于找对问题
it's finding the questions.
看谁能找出最关键的问题
We need the man who can find the key question.
对了 阿诺德 换个话题
By the way, Arnold, to change the subject completely,
你退休之后打算干什么?      啊 非常好的问题
what will you be doing when you retire? Ah, very good question!
问得好      也许有工作要你做
Very good question. There might be jobs you could pick up,
继续为国效力 不管你的接班人是谁
ways you could serve the country, which your successor
他能给你安排...呃...说服你接受
could put your way er, persuade you to undertake!
我确实有些打算 你看
I had been giving it some thought
有人请我做西方银行的董事长
I'll be chairman of the Banque Occidentale
IBM和英国石油也有我一席
and there'll be directorships of IBM and BP and so on.
不过我想...      如何?
But I was thinking... Yes?
皇家剧院基金会明年要选主席了
The Chairmanship of the Opera House will be coming up
剧院基金会主席...      还有牛津大学名誉校长
Chairman of Covent Garden... And the chancellorship of Oxford.
英格兰银行副长一职也很...
The deputy chairmanship of the Bank of England would be a...
有挑战性?      挑战性 没错
...A challenge? A challenge, exactly.
还有国安委员会主席
And head of the Security Commission.
英国－加勒比协会会长更是...
The Anglo-Caribbean Association would give one...
造福大众的机遇
...a chance to be of service.
正是
Precisely!
尤其在冬天
Especially during the winter months.
我看合格的接班人一定能安排妥当 阿诺德
I'm sure any successor worth his salt could arrange these.
你这么想?那我总算放心了
Do you think so? That's very reassuring, very reassuring.
还有另一件事
But there is another thing.
有人对首相提出的建议
Certain advice one may have given the Prime Minister
如果披露出来 会遭到误解
could, if it emerged, be misinterpreted.
什么建议呢?      非常合情合理的
Er, what sort of advice? All sensible and reasonable,
关于罢工中出动军队
but advice about using troops during strikes.
为安全起见 当然要适当武装
A very sensible precaution that they should be armed,
然而建议要配机关枪...
but, taken out of context, machine guns...
哦 这种事绝对没必要披露出去
Oh, I'm sure that need never come out.
我还建议过和南非商讨恢复非洲海军基地的事
Negotiations about reactivating the Simonstown naval base.
战略上绝对无可厚非
Absolutely sensible strategically
在马岛事件中尤其有用
a great help with the Falklands,
但如果一个人要当联邦秘书长...
but as Secretary-General of the Commonwealth...
那就尴尬了 不消说你一定会当上联邦秘书长
And you will be Secretary-General of the Commonwealth.
会吗?借你吉言啰
Would I? How gratifying!
我看合格的接班人一定能妥善保管这些文件
And the right successor would keeping those files under wraps.
很好
Good.
那么 话说回去
Anyway, to get back to our original point,
各位同仁与我都同意你就是第一候选人
My colleagues and I can placing your name top of the list.
这样啊
I see.
能否请问还有多少候选人?
May I ask how many other names will be on the list?
哦 我可找不出第二个合格的了
Oh, I don't think there's anyone else who's up to scratch.
再来一杯
Have another drink.
顺便告诉你 我会出任信息自由运动主席
I'll be the presidency of the Campaign for Freedom of Information.
信息自由?这从何说起?
Freedom of Information?! What on earth for?
反对党很欢迎 今日反对党便是明日执政党
Well, it's very popular with the Opposition
也可以保证信息自由不被滥用
and it will mean one can ensure that the freedom is not abused.
干杯 敬可靠政府代代相传
So, here's to the continuity of sound government.
也敬信息自由
And freedom of information.
以国家利益为准绳      哦
Whenever it's in the national interest. Oh, yes!
大臣 我有个不幸的消息      什么 汉弗莱?
Minister, I have some very grave news. Yes, Humphrey?
与您共掌此部至今 细细想来
The relationship, which I might tentatively aver
虽不敢说肝胆相照 荣辱与共
has been not without a degree of reciprocal utility
倒也合作愉快 相得益彰
and even occasional gratification,
如今却面临分道扬镳 一言以蔽之
is approaching a point of irreversible bifurcation and, to be brief,
已经走到了令人痛心 无可挽回的终点
is in the propinquity of its ultimate, regrettable, termination.
这样啊
I see.
我...要走了      什么?
I'm... on my way out. What?
命里有时终须有 当一人天数将至...
One has to accept what fate has in store, when one passes on
天数将至?!
Passes on?!
将去到水草丰美之地
...to pastures new, perhaps greener...
脱胎换骨 献身于至高无上之权威
In the service of one who is greater than any of us.
汉弗莱 我太痛心了      谢谢您 大臣
Humphrey, I'm so sorry! Thank you, Minister.
你夫人知道吗?      她一直有所察觉
Does Lady Appleby know? She's suspected it for some time.
什么时候通知你的?      今天下午
When did they tell you? This afternoon.
你还有多少时间?      哦 几星期而已
How long do they give you? Just a few weeks.
几星期?
Weeks?!
足够我把余下的事务理清了
It'll give me enough time to sort everything out.
汉弗莱 你真是英勇
Humphrey, you're so terribly brave!
紧张是难免的 前路茫茫 总让人恐惧
One is a little anxious. One is always wary of the unknown
但我坚信我能应付到底
but I have faith I'll muddle through.
大臣 您怎么了?
Minister, what's the matter?
对不起 汉弗莱
I'm sorry, Humphrey.
想我们同甘共苦这么多年...
It's just we've had our ups and downs, but...
大臣 没必要太难过
Oh, Minister, don't take on so!
我们还会常常见面的
We'll still see one another regularly.
至少每周见一次吧      什么?
Yes, once a week at least. What?
我还没说我要去哪里      啊?
I haven't told you where I'm going yet. Eh?
我已经被任命为内阁秘书
I have been appointed Secretary to the Cabinet.
内阁秘书?      对呀 您以为是什么?
Secretary to the Cabinet? Why, what did you think?
我...还以为...还以为...
I... I thought... I thought...
真对不起 我今天太累 有点反常
Sorry about crying. I'm not myself today, a little tired.
这些工作啊 你知道....
Overwrought. Things have been, you know...
我真遗憾
I am so sorry.
也许作为预备内阁秘书
Perhaps as Cabinet Secretary designate
我可以建议首相为您减轻负担...
I should suggest some lightening of the load...
别误会 我很好 真的      那就好
No, no. Don't misunderstand me. I'm fine, fine! Good, good.
这么说你要当内阁秘书了      对
So, you're going to be Cabinet Secretary. Yes.
内阁秘书呀      嗯
Cabinet Secretary! Mm-hmm.
内阁的秘书      是
Secretary to the Cabinet! YES!
那太光荣了 恭喜 汉弗莱     谢谢您
That's a great honour. Congratulations. Thank you.
不过 这样一来你和我就...      很遗憾 是的
'Course, that means that you and I... Alas, yes.
我怎么办呢?      可能您没了我更好
How shall I manage? Probably even better without me.
对 可能...不不不 没那事
Yes, I probably... No, no, certainly not, no!
汉弗莱 你要让首相也见识见识你对付我那套...
You're going to do for the PM what you've always done to me.
帮助我
For me!
首相的左右手
PM's right-hand man.
参谋政务      正是
Advising on issues. Quite so.
还有...人事 对吧
And, er, and people, no doubt.
大臣?
Minister?
汉弗莱      什么事 大臣?
Humphrey... Yes, Minister?
我想说 我一直觉得你非常优秀
I want you to know I think you've been absolutely wonderful.
我极其崇敬你做的一切工作
Highest admiration for all you've done
非常出色 非常出色
Wonderful work. Wonderful work.
公务员传统的典范      大臣 您过奖了
Finest tradition of the service. Minister, you're too kind.
希望你也觉得我...我的...
I just hope you feel that I... In my...
一直以来...这个...
When things are... Well, it...
说起来...
If it should come up, er...
我们两个一向合作无间 对吧?
I think we've made a jolly good team here, you and I?
我没法盼望比您更好的大臣
I couldn't have wished for a better Minister
汉弗莱 你太好了
Humphrey, you're too kind!
你升迁的事什么时候通报部里?
When are you going to tell the staff?
周五晚上 官方正式宣布之前
On Friday evening, just before it's promulgated.
我会借圣诞酒会向大家告别      那可太开心了
I will bid them farewell at the Christmas party
并且痛心      痛心 对
And sad. Sad, yes, sad.
痛心之至
Terribly sad.
玩得好吗?      很好 谢谢 大臣
Enjoying yourself? Yes, thank you, Minister.
玩得好吗?      谢谢 酒会很好
Enjoying yourself? Yes, Minister. Lovely party.
是的大臣 真是太开心了      放纵一下总是好的
Yes, it's frightfully good fun. Always good to let your hair down.
好吧 现在我想说几句
Right, now I think it's time I said a few words.
此时此刻对我们所有人都有重大意义
This is a very, very special occasion for us all.
四海升平 诸君幸福美满
Peace on Earth, goodwill to all men.
抱歉 是“诸位”
Sorry, persons!
很高兴能和大家欢聚一堂 诸位都是为我...
Good to have this little get-together who've served me, er...
与我...为我...与我一同
...worked with me... for me... no, with me
效力于这个行事...
here at the Department of Adminis...
政事行务...
...Ministry of Administr...
行政部
...at the DAA.
我们是个团队 就像内阁 除了我们站同一边
We're a team, like the Cabinet, except we're all on the same side...
并不是说内阁就...不过 我是说影子内阁
Not that the Cabinet... Well, I meant... really, the shadow Cabinet.
如此佳节 就不谈政治了
Let's keep politics out of this. Season of goodwill.
这就是为什么圣诞期间不召开国会
That's why Parliament doesn't sit over Christmas!
我也要祝各位万事如意 当官的也一样
Season of goodwill. Even to one's officials!
我还能说什么呢?敬小汉
Well, what can I say? Humphrey.
敬汉弗莱阿普比爵士      敬汉弗莱阿普比爵士
(BERNARD) Sir Humphrey Appleby! (ALL) Sir Humphrey Appleby!
谢谢 首先我衷心感谢各位
Thank you. I'd just like to thank you all for
多年以来的辛勤工作
all the hard work you've done all these years.
如此时刻总令人心中五味杂陈 悲欣交集
Occasion like this engenders a certain emotional ambiguity
他在交集啥?      尽管他可以说
What's he ambigulous about? While one is, one should say,
他的离别乃是一种荣光 却也不免黯然
honoured by the cause of departure, saddened by the fact
尤其不忍告别其职业生涯中无可比拟的大臣阁下
in particular leave the service of a Minister without parallel
说得真好
I say, that's jolly decent.
打破这独特的伙伴关系      确实独特
A unique partnership. Absolutely unique.
最后请让我祝各位圣诞快乐
So I should end by wishing a happy Christmas to you all,
尤其为我们的大臣 尽管相聚时光短暂
In particular to a Minister in the brief time with us
我们仍可以看出他日渐庄严 稳健 从不动摇
we've watched grow in standing, stature and sureness of touch.
最后 祝大家新年快乐
So, seasonal felicitations to you all,
不过 请牢牢记住内政大臣的节日号召
Do remember the Home Secretary's campaign for the holiday:
圣诞期间 请别酒后驾车
Don't drink and drive this Christmas.
我要为这个干一杯...哎呀抱歉
I'll drink to that! ...Oh, dear, I'm sorry!
真的应该让我来开 吉姆      我开得非常稳
I do wish you'd let me drive, Jim. I'm driving perfectly stably.
稳倒稳 不过天亮之前总得到家吧
True, but we have to get home before dawn!
晚上好 警罐先生 生蛋快乐
Good evening, Cinstable. Happy Crispsmas.
请出示驾照 先生      好的
May I see your licence, sir? Certainly.
您是吉姆哈克先生吧?      没错
Aren't you Mr Jim Hacker? That's right.
有问题吗?      您为什么开这么慢?
What's trouble? Why you driving so slowly?
我不想被马路牙子撞...
I didn't want the kerb to hit me...
不想撞上马路牙子
I didn't want to hit the kerb.
等等 我有交通银章
Look, I've got a silver badge somewhere.
好吧 不如让伊万警官替您开车
I see. Perhaps Constable Evans can drive you
不必了 警官 我来开
It's all right, Officer. I'll drive.
好吧 哈克夫人 如果您的状态适合驾驶的话
OK, Mrs Hacker. If you're in a proper state to drive.
我不喝酒 警官 至少在我丈夫开车的时候
I don't drink, Officer. Well, not when my husband's driving.
我也是 基本没喝
Nor do I, hardly.
请进来      你这小地方不错嘛 汉弗莱
There we are. Nice little place you have here, Humphrey.
谢谢 大臣      第一次内阁会议主持得挺好
Thank you. You handled your first Cabinet meeting well.
坐在首相身边感觉怎样?      您请坐 大臣
What was it like sitting next to the PM? Do sit down, Minister.
请您来喝咖啡 是因为
I've asked you to drop in for a coffee because
内政部报告我一起交通事故
the Home Office informs me of a traffic incident.
我明白了      这完全是您的私事
Yes, I see. It's entirely your own affair...
那当然      但据说首相看得很重
Precisely. But the PM takes a grave view.
他认为大臣应当以身作则
He feels Ministers should set an example
汉弗莱 你不是在训斥我吧?
You're not ticking me off, are you?
哪里话 大臣 我只是卑微的内阁办事员
I'm only a servant a humble functionary.
但我得向内政部保证下不为例
But I need to assure the Home Office it won't occur again.
那银章是干吗用的?      这是一项特权 大臣
What silver badges for? It's a special privilege, Minister.
特许我们驶入警戒线或在禁止停车处停车
Pass through police cordons and park in prohibited areas
并不是保护酒后驾车用的
It is not to protect drunks who drive cars.
我不要挨办事员的训 你这种地位的也不行
I will not be lectured by a functionary
我是堂堂御前大臣      当然 大臣 我十分抱歉
I'm a Minister of the Crown. Yes, of course. I do apologise.
我会照您的意思 上报女王陛下
I will inform the Crown of the incident if that is your wish.
我...
I...
算了 你可以告诉内务部我接受教训了
Now I think of it, you can tell the Home Office I take the point.
谢谢您 大臣      内务部长知道吗?
Thank you, Minister. Does the Home Secretary himself know?
这倒无所谓
It hardly matters.
恐怕内务部长没有您幸运
I'm afraid the Home Secretary has not been as lucky as you were,
所以他今天没出席内阁
which is why he wasn't at Cabinet.
您也知道 他亲自发起"圣诞勿酒后驾车"运动
He initiated "Don't drink and drive" campaign
命令警方"严惩肇事者"
and ordered the police to "get tough".
不幸的是
Well, unfortunately...
昨晚他也因酒后驾车被捕 在他自己的选区
he, too, was picked up last night for drunken driving
您看旗帜晚报第一版了吗?
Have you seen the first edition of the Standard?
他的警卫员哪去了?      显然被他甩掉了
Where on earth was his security man? He'd given him the slip.
您知道这些醉鬼多狡猾
You know how cunning these drunks can be.
这事难道不能遮过去?用银章呢?
Couldn't they have hushed it up? Silver badge job?
他的情况特殊 他撞翻了一台卡车
His case was rather different. He caused a lorry to overturn
里面满载核废料
It was full of nuclear waste.
他弹回来 正中地方报纸主编的车
rebounded into a car driven by the editor of a local newspaper.
不会吧
Oh, no.
自然就泄漏了      核废料?
Inevitably, it leaked out. The nuclear waste?
不 是消息
No, the story.
内务大臣非辞职不可了      唉 可不是
The Home Secretary will have to resign. Alas, yes.
要把他怎样呢?      这个嘛
What will happen to him? Well...
既然他醉得跟个爵爷一样
I gather he was as drunk as a lord
大概要冷藏一阵 然后封个爵吧
so after a discreet interval, they'll probably make him one!
他肯定被留下了
He's obviously been held up.
你等的时候 可以帮忙贴贴邮票
You can stamp some cards if you like.
不是给选民的吗?      是
Aren't they to constituents? Yes.
那就不是政府行为 是政治行为 我无权插手
That's political activity. I'm not allowed to help.
要是给记者的呢?      那就可以
If they're to journalists? That'd be OK.
这些是给记者的      好
They're to journalists. Fine.
恐怕媒体公关的本质就是一个个舔过来
Licking is essential of relationships with the press.
我听说内阁要改组      对 新闻可能会报
I hear the reshuffle is about to be announced.
我喜欢看新闻 最容易找到吉姆在哪
It's my best chance of finding out where Jim is.
此事显然与美国军方有联系
There was no question of American military involved.
插播一条简讯 来自唐宁街10号
We've j'ust had a newsflash from Number 10 Downing Street.
首相将于新年期间提前退休
The Prime Minister is to retire early in the New Year.
他声称不打算进入下届议会
He does not want to serve in another Parliament,
以便接班人顺利执政 继而参加普选
giving his successor a good run-up to the next election.
我们将尽快播发后续报道
We'll bring you further news as soon as we can.
听见没有?      听见了
(ALL) Have you heard? (ALL) Yes!
内阁紧急会议就说这个      怎么这么突然?
The emergency Cabinet meeting was to tell us. Why so suddenly?
首相说是为了便于接班人参选
He said to give his successor a good run-up to the next election
所以肯定不是为这个
so that can't be the reason.
那为什么?      有各种神奇的流言
Why, then? Some extraordinary rumours are going about.
左翼说他是中情局的密探
The left say he's a secret CIA agent.
右翼说他是克格勃的密探
The right say he's a secret KGB agent
大臣 我听到的完全不同
Minister, I've heard something quite different,
说有价值一百万的南非钻石
that there is ? million-worth of diamonds from South Africa
藏在唐宁街保险箱里
in a Downing Street safe,
但这只是流言      真的假的?
but it's only a rumour. Is that true?
真的
Yes.
这么说唐宁街真有钻石
So, there ARE all those diamonds in Downing Street!
有吗?      你说有的
Are there? You said there were!
我没说      你说了
I didn't. You did!
你说有流言 我问真的假的 你说是真的
I said is the rumour true, you said yes!
真的有这流言
True it's a rumour.
你听说是真的      真的只是听说
You heard it was true! True I heard it!
抱歉打扰你们的重要谈话 不过你相信吗?
Sorry to cut in, but do you believe it?
我相信我听说过
I believe I heard it.
钻石吗?不信      不可能吗?
Oh, about the diamonds? No. Is it impossible?
不是 不过官方从未否认过
No, but it's never been officially denied.
政治第一定律 只有官方否认的才可信
First rule of politics: Never believe anything until it's officially denied.
会举行普选吗?      没必要
Will there be a general election? There's no need.
我们已经是多数派了 选个新党魁就行
The majority's big enough. We'll just choose a new leader.
你想当吗?      我?没指望
Do you want the job? Me? No chance!
要么埃里克 要么邓肯
It'll either be Eric or Duncan.
本来是雷的 他是副党魁
It should have been Ray. He was Deputy Leader.
不过他得辞去内政部长职位...
But as he's had to resign as Home Secretary...
当然 所以首相要辞职      为什么?
Of course! That's why the PM resigned! (BERNARD) Why?
他一向讨厌雷 他拖到今天
He's always hated Ray. He just hung on
就为了避免副党魁上位
to make sure his deputy didn't get the leadership!
就像艾德礼对付莫里森
Like Attlee and Morrison.
所以他辞职 好让新党魁趁普选前进入10号?
So it is to give time for the new leader to be run in?
现在内政部长可进去了
Now that the Home Secretary's been run in
埃里克想要我支持他
Eric wants my support for the leadership.
他很合适 他是个成功的财政部长
He could be the right man. He's been a fairly successful Chancellor.
我已经暗示我会...倒向他
I've already indicated that I'm... on his side.
邓肯呢?      对 邓肯也不错
What about Duncan? Yes, Duncan could be the man.
他在外交部干得挺好
He's done fairly well at the Foreign Office.
我打算支持邓肯
I think I'll support Duncan
你支持埃里克和邓肯两个?
You're supporting Eric AND Duncan?
无所谓 如果我支持埃里克而邓肯赢了 没办法
It's all very well, but if I support Eric and Duncan gets it, that's it.
如果我支持邓肯而埃里克赢了
If I support Duncan and Eric gets it
也没办法      干脆两边都不支持
that's it. Don't support either!
那谁赢了 我都没办法      你到底支持谁?
Whoever gets it, that's it. So who are you supporting?
邓肯
Duncan.
或者埃里克
Or Eric.
邓肯争议太大 要是为党派着想
Duncan's so divisive. It really would be for the good of the party,
为国家着想      埃里克 我怎么能...
the good of the country... Eric, I don't see how I can.
你的支持至关重要 你人缘好
Your support would be crucial. You're universally popular...
我不知道...      公众形象好
I don't know... Good public image...
没错      大家都说你可靠
Yes... Regarded as sound.
是吗?      所以如果你倒向我这边
Am I? So, if you put your weight behind me...
可我毕竟是党主席
You see my problem as chairman of the party.
如果邓肯当选呢?你就惨了      这个嘛...
What would happen if Duncan got it? Disaster! Well...
告诉你 我连外交部都不给他
Tell you what. I wouldn't keep him at the Foreign Office.
我要任命新外交部长
I'd look for a new Foreign Secretary.
我说过 我必须表现得中立
But as I said, I must appear impartial.
不过如果有办法暗示我的支持...
But if there could be ways of hinting at my support for you...
暗示得完全中立
...in a perfectly impartial way...
可是邓肯 作为党主席...
But Duncan, as chairman of the party...
正因为你是主席 分量才重
As such you carry even more weight.
你没树过什么敌 暂时还没有
You haven't got any real enemies. Not yet, anyway.
但职责要求我保持中立
But it's my job to be impartial.
要是埃里克当选 国家就遭殃了      对
If Eric got into Number 10 it'd be catastrophic. Yes...
吉姆 我们在同一战线吧?
Jim, we're on the same side, aren't we?
对      那就好
Yes. Good.
我一定会赢 我不会忘掉跟我作对的人
I'm going to win and I never forgive people who let me down.
我不能太公开支持
I can't make my support too public.
不用公开 大家心里清楚就好
It doesn't have to be public, just so long as everybody knows.
等我进了10号 埃里克去了北爱尔兰...
Then when I'm in Number 10, and Eric's in Northern Ireland...
谁做财政部长就很清楚了 对吧?      是吗?
we know who'll be the next Chancellor, don't we? Do we?
你是说...?
You mean...?
还是你自己想去北爱尔兰?
Unless you fancy Northern Ireland yourself?
信息自由运动进展如何?
How are things at the Campaign for the Freedom of Information?
抱歉 我无权透露
Sorry, I can't talk about that.
新首相会是我们伟大的财长
So, will the new PM be our eminent Chancellor
还是卓越的外长呢?
or our distinguished Foreign Secretary?
我正想问你 你觉得应该是谁?
Well, which do you think it should be?
不好说 这就像选个疯子管理精神病院
Difficult. Like asking which lunatic should run the asylum.
问题是 他们都信奉干涉主义 要是当首相
Trouble is, they're both interventionists with notions
一定事必躬亲     谁站我们这边?
if they became PM. Have we any allies?
许多人 尤其是总组织秘书
Quite a few, the Chief Whip particularly.
他担心谁当选都会
He's worried that who gets the job will
清算对手的支持者
antagonise the other's supporters
使党派分裂      所以要另找个折衷的
and split the party. So we need a compromise candidate.
嗯 可塑性强的
Hmm. Malleable.
灵活的      随和的
Flexible. Likeable.
立场不坚定      观点不突出
No firm opinions. No bright ideas.
思维不敏锐      没能力改变现状
Not intellectually committed. No strength of purpose to change anything.
公认的好操纵 懂得接受引导
Someone who can be manipulated, professionally guided.
将国家大事留给专家处理
leave the business of government in the hands of the experts.
天呐 天呐 天呐 办不到
Oh, dear, oh, dear, oh, dear! It's impossible.
怎么?政府里很多人喜欢不干涉的领导
A lot would welcome a less-interventionist leader.
那两个候选人不喜欢      可以说服他们
Not the other two candidates! They might be persuaded.
什么 让他们退出?
What, to stand aside?
你看了他们的军情五处档案吗?
Yes. Have you seen their Ml5 files?
没有      一定要看内阁大臣的安全档案
No. Always send for Cabinet Ministers' Ml5 files
如果你想找乐子的话
if you enjoy a good laugh!
哦 伯纳      爵士
Oh, Bernard. Sir.
就这些      多谢你
Just... Thank you very much.
请坐下      谢谢
Do sit down. Thank you.
顺便 新年快乐      多谢您
Happy New Year, by the way. Thank you.
好的
Right.
那么
So...
这是我在行政部最后一件事了
...this is our very last piece of DAA business
恐怕是的 汉弗莱爵士
Yes, I'm afraid so, Sir Humphrey.
啊 好吧
Ah, well.
伯纳 我问你个问题
Bernard, just let me ask you something.
你愿不愿意你的现任上司...
What would you say to your present master...
当下届首相?
...as the next Prime Minister?
你说大臣?      对
The Minister? Yes.
哈克先生?      对
Mr Hacker? Yes.
当首相?      对
As Prime Minister? Yes.
你赶时间吗?
Are you in a hurry?
不 我看看今天是不是愚人节
Just checking it's not April 1st.
你觉得你的大臣当不了首相吗?
you mean your Minister is not up to Prime Minister?
当然不 阿诺德爵士 我没资格...
Oh, no, Sir Arnold, it's not for me to, er...
我是说...当然...我认为他...
Well, I mean... Of course, I'm... I'm sure he's, er...
哦 天呐
Oh, gosh!
许多人看到这一委任有种种好处
There are many advantages in the appointment.
对英国      对英国
For Britain. For Britain.
对 好吧      所以我们交待给你
Yes, well, yes... So we trust you
确保你的大臣未来几周内
to ensure your Minister does nothing incisive
不要过激 不要引起争议
or divisive over the next few weeks.
避免一切反对意见      任何事都不要明确表态
Expresses no firm opinion about anything.
明白了吗?      好吧 反正他本来也打算这么做
is that clear? I think that's what he was planning anyway.
这一切都是为什么 伯纳?
What's it all for, Bernard?
我们在做什么? 有什么意义?
What are we all doing? What does it all mean?
我没学过神学 大臣
I didn't read theology, Minister.
全是无用功 就说昨晚欧共体的宴会
The waste of it all. Take that EEC reception last night.
汉弗莱向我介绍一位官员
Humphrey introduced me to an official
专门雇佣农民生产过剩粮食
who pays farmers to produce surplus food
又介绍另一位 他雇佣人们销毁过剩粮食
and then another official who pays to destroy the surpluses.
然后雇几千名官僚制造大批公文 让他们运转
Then they pay thousands of bureaucrats to make it all work.
看了这些 你不郁闷吗 伯纳?
Doesn't the futility of it all depress you?
不 大臣 我是公务员
Not really. I'm a civil servant.
我和埃里克和邓肯都谈过了
I've been talking to Eric and Duncan.
我好像答应支持埃里克
I think I've promised to support Eric's candidature.
好吧      然后我好像又答应支持邓肯
I see. Then I think I promised to support Duncan's.
这很公平 大臣
That sounds very even-handed, Minister.
对 但我总要食言一次 雪利酒?
But I can't keep both promises. Sherry?
谢谢您 这只是政治许诺而已吧 大臣
Thank you. They were only political promises.
对...怎么讲?
Yes... What do you mean?
就像您的竞选纲领 人们会理解的
I mean, like your manifesto promises, people understand.
没错
Yes.
问题在于 他们俩也没明确许诺我什么
But non of them made any categorical promises to me.
那您就没顾虑了      当然有 我总得支持一方
Then you have no problem. Have decide who to support.
不仅仅是押宝的问题 我的态度举足轻重
It's not just picking the winner. My support could tip the balance.
问题在于我想做外长还是财长?
Do I want to be Foreign Secretary or Exchequer?
都不想 是吗?      为什么不呢?
Neither, do you? Why not?
两边都是苦差
They're both such terrible jobs!
你说的可是内阁三大宝座之二
You're talking about two of the top three Cabinet jobs.
我明白 大臣
I realise that.
伯纳 你是公务员 你不懂政治      抱歉
As a civil servant, you don't understand politics. Sorry.
政治成功就在于曝光
To be a success, you have to be in the limelight.
财政部长受万众瞩目 一定能增加选票
You have a very high profile as Chancellor of the Exchequer
你明白吧?      对 可是恕我直言 大臣
You see now, don't you? But with respect, Minister...
财政部长最煞风景 他得提高烟酒税率
The Chancellor is Mr Killjoy. Raising taxes on beer and cigarettes
降低公共设施预算 很招选民怨恨
cutting down public spending goes badly with electorate.
我还是别当财政部长了 根本没出路
Maybe I don't want to be Chancellor of the Exchequer.
没有 大臣 除非他们再挤兑您去管外交部
Unless you're sent to the Foreign Office as punishment.
挤兑?      对 这个工作更惨
Punishment? It's an even worse job.
国外赚不到选票?      正是
No votes in Foreign Affairs? Exactly.
外交部善待外国人 国民却希望越狠越好
The FCO loves foreigners, but the British people don't.
可不是
Quite.
从世界局势看来 外交部可有可无
As far as world politics goes, the Foreign Office is an irrelevance.
我们又没有实权 就是个美军导弹基地
We've no real power. We're just an American missile base!
没错 大臣
Yes, Minister.
前有虎穴 后有狼窝
Between the devil and the deep blue sea.
除非...您还有一种选择
Unless... Of course, there is one other option.
是什么?      中间路线
What other option? Do the middle job.
中间?内政部吗?管那些抢劫 越狱 种族骚乱?
Home Secretary? Responsible for all the muggings, race riots?
免了吧 谢谢      不是 是获取所有功劳的职位
No, thank you! No, be the one who takes all the credit.
你指什么?该不会...
What do you mean? You mean...?
你不是说...?
You don't mean...?
你真的是说...?
You do mean...?
那么 组织秘书处意下如何?
How's it all looking from the Chief Whip's office?
你知道 如果埃里克当选
You know, If Eric gets it
不出三个月党派就会分裂
we'll have a party split in three months.
要是邓肯 不出三个星期
If it's Duncan, it'll take three weeks.
杰弗里 首相要我对你寄予完全信任
Geoffrey, the PM's asked me to take you into my confidence.
本不该告诉你 但是怎么说呢 他们有安全问题
I shouldn't tell you but there are security question marks
两位候选人都有
over both the current candidates.
什么安全问题?      唉 我不能透露
What question marks? Alas, I can say no more.
首相不在 这又是党内事务
The only person I can disclose this to in the PM's absence,
我只能透露给一个人 就是党主席
and as it is a party matter, is the chairman of the party.
吉姆哈克      对 他答应会来
Jim Hacker. He's promised to join us.
不过眼下 党内有折衷的候选人吗?
But do you think the party can find a compromise candidate?
少说有五六个      你考虑过党主席本人吗?
Could be half a dozen. Have you considered the chairman?
吉姆哈克?
Jim Hacker?!
吉姆哈克...
Jim Hacker...
有可能的 对不对?
Yes, it is possible, isn't it?
毕竟 更糟的首相我们也选过
After all, there have been less likely Prime Ministers.
对...
Yes...
哪位?
Who?
肯定有的吧
Oh, there must have been!
抱歉
Sorry
什么?好的 请他进来
Yes? Oh, all right. Send him in.
大臣 您能来太好了
Minister, so good of you to call.
亨利      早安
Henry. Morning.
请坐
Do sit down. Minister...
大臣 我有个问题 想请您帮忙
...I have a problem and I need your help.
天啊天啊 你一个人治理不了国家吗?
Oh, dear! Can't you run the country on your own?
是的 恐怕状况很严重      对 当然
It is a rather grave matter, I'm afraid. Yes, of course.
事关大选 首相不得不请您来商议
About the election. The PM felt we had to call you in.
到这地步啦?
That bad, eh?
有某些秘密信息
There are certain items of confidential information
尽管从理论上看来无可厚非
In theory might be susceptible of interpretation,
却也不乏含糊暧昧之处
do nevertheless contain a sufficient element of ambiguity,
如果存心不以善意度之
were they to be presented in a less than generous manner,
可能会造成尴尬 甚至有
might be a source of great embarrassment and even hazard
危及高度敏感机关公信力之虞
to impinge upon the deliberations of more sensitivity.
你说什么?
I'm sorry?
他是说安全问题      安全问题?怎么讲?
About security question marks. Security? What do you mean?
机密      我知道什么是安全问题
Secrets. I know what security means.
但你什么意思?      我又没权知道
But what do you mean? I'm not allowed to know.
为什么?      安全问题
Why not? Security.
您看 大臣 既然首相不在 党务由您负责
Since in the PM's absence you are deputising on party matters,
请看这个 财政大臣的安全档案
I can show you the file on the Chancellor of the Exchequer?
理论上讲 不该给您看 但是...
Technically, I can't show you any of it, but, er...
基于目前局势 我感到您必须有所了解
under the circumstances, I can show you relevant items.
这是安全部门的报告摘要
Here's a summary of the reports from the security services.
政治保安处...
Special Branch...
给您
There we are.
对了 他司机的供述
Interview with his driver.
还有首相的私人备忘
And the PM's confidential memo.
当然都严格保密      当然
Strictest secrecy, of course. Of course.
老色...
Dirty old...!
真想不到他还有这闲工夫
You wouldn't have thought he had the time,
埃里克那种工作狂
a workaholic like Eric.
我发现在一个领域活跃的人
I've found that people who are highly active in one area
一般其它领域也不弱
tend to be equally active in all the others.
谁能看出他这么热爱...
You wouldn't think he went in for...
似乎时下的说法是"平行慢跑" 大臣
I understand the current expression is horizontal jogging
这些事都有年头了吧 证据也不确凿
All this was some time ago and it doesn't seem very conclusive.
对对 所以首相让他当财长
That's why the PM thought it all right for him to be Chancellor.
但说到南斯拉夫那位和南非的两位
But the Yugoslavian one and the two South Africans,
更不用提阿根廷那位神秘女士...
not to mention the shady lady from Argentina...
有人觉得她只是个幌子      幌子?怎么讲?
And it's thought she's just a cover anyway. Cover? What for?
我的天
Good heavens!
如果这些女士都是幌子
If all these ladies were just covers
那他到底有什么...需求?
what on earth were his real requirements?
我还真没法说      哦
I really can't tell you. Ooh!
所以国防部和外交部就比较微妙了
So it was thought that Foreign Office might be too delicate.
那可不是      如果他当上首相
I can see that! Then, if he were PM...
安全部门也会落到他手中 后果不堪设想
Head of security services as well. It's unthinkable.
你是说得选邓肯
You're saying it's got to be Duncan.
我正要提这个 这是他的档案
I was coming to that. This is his file.
还是政治保安处
Special Branch again.
反商业欺诈局...
Then we have the Fraud Squad...
国税局...
Inland Revenue...
秘密核算报告 英格兰银行汇票副本
Bank of England foreign exchange division...
您想看多少?
How much do you want?
这些事当时都是合法的吧?
All this was technically legal at the time, wasn't it?
对 理论上也许合法 但他就不能再当财长
Yes but it ruled him out of consideration for the Treasury.
这些都哪来的 军情五处?
How did they get all this Ml5?
这个 只能说已经卷入够深了
let's just say it's all been gone into quite enough.
就像那位神秘女士
Like the shady lady!
这也太劲爆了吧      问我干吗 我又没看
Isn't it all astounding? I don't know. I haven't seen it
汉弗莱 不要以为我笨...      哦 大臣 说哪里话
Don't think me foolish. Oh, Minister, perish the thought
对不起 杰弗里来干什么?      不能冒这个险
Geoffrey. Why are you here? We dare not allow these scandals.
丑闻抖出去 党派和国家都脸上无光
If they are, it would embarrass the country and the party
如果他俩之一当选的话
if either of them became head of government.
我们可不想被人光着屁股抓住      就像埃里克
We can't be caught with our trousers down. Like Eric!
明白了
I see.
确实 事态很严重
Yes, this is serious.
非常严重      非常严重
Very serious. Very serious.
要是他俩之一上台会怎样?      那就严重了
What happens if one them became PM? Something very serious
非常严重      确实
Very serious. I see.
严重的后果      严重的后果
Serious repercussions... Serious repercussions...
极其严重之至
...of the utmost seriousness.
对 还真是严重
Yes, that is serious.
实际上 我敢说严重到不能再严重
I would say that it could hardly be more serious.
好吧 至少我们都同意 确实挺严重
Well, I think we're all agreed, then, this is serious.
对
Yes.
现在怎么办?
What happens now?
党内得提出新候选人 要快
The party needs to agree on another candidate, quick.
组织秘书想问您有没有人选      作为党主席
The Chief Whip wondered if you had any ideas As Party Chairman
这可难说了
Well, it's rather difficult.
你们要找一个出类拔萃的人 做首相的料
You're looking for a potential Prime Minister.
他得可靠      对
Someone who's sound. Yes.
随和
Likeable.
灵活
Flexible.
对 健全
Yes. Normal.
有凝聚力      对
Solvent. Yes.
党内两翼都能接受
And acceptable to both wings of the party.
并且要懂得采纳意见 大臣
And someone who understands how to take advice
对 这个...
Yes. Well...
天呐 得推荐谁呢?
Gosh! Who can I suggest?
您自己想不想干?      我?
Have you thought of doing the job yourself? Me?!
怎么不行?      您不愿意当首相?
Why not? Wouldn't you want to be Prime Minister?
当然愿意 不过...责任重大啊
I'd love to be, but... It's a very big job
我不一定当得起 首相呀
I'm not sure I could. Prime Minister!
也许大臣自认为算不上国家栋梁之才
Perhaps He feels he's not Prime Ministerial calibre.
绝对没那回事 汉弗莱
There isn't any doubt about that, Humphrey
不不 我也不那么想 不过您在犹豫
No, not in my mind. But you seem hesitant.
做人要谦虚嘛 但我自信我能胜任
Modesty forbids. But I have no doubt I can do the job.
谦虚之至 大臣      还剩一个问题
Modestly put. There's only one fly in the ointment.
公众不太认识你
You're a bit of an outsider
未来几天你能不能高调打场大胜仗?
Can you organise some public success in the next few days?
有点麻烦 我正陷在欧洲香肠堆里呢
A tall order. I'm up to my neck in the Euro sausage!
不能发动宣传 让大家知道我有意参选吗?
Won't it be enough to let people know I want the job?
恰恰相反 最好让大家知道你绝无此意
Quite the reverse! Better to let people know you DON'T want it.
这就够了?      对 只要您跟谁都这么说
Would that be enough? If you tell everybody that, yes.
宣传我来做 您只说您完全没这个野心
Leave it to me. Say you have no ambitions in that direction.
好吧 可如果有人问"你不愿负责任吗?"
Supposing somebody says, "Do you refuse to stand?"
你知道 媒体会下套      大臣 我无权多嘴 不过
the media try to trap you. It's not my place, but
一贯的回答是 "尽管一个人不谋其位"
previously answer was "While one does not seek the office
"他仍以造福国家为己任"
"one has pledged oneself to the service of one's country,
"若是众望所归 唯有上台才最能造福国家"
"and if friends persuade one that was the best way to serve
"他也只能担起责任来"
"one might have to accept the responsibility
"完全舍弃自己的私心"
whatever one's own private wishes might be."
"舍弃私心..." 好吧 我记住了
"...private wishes might be." Yes, I think I've got that.
那就有三派候选人了
So, it's a three-way election, then.
若能团结一致 那是最好 公众喜欢团结
it should be an unopposed. Unity sits well with the public.
党内也会欢迎      埃里克和邓肯不会
The party will welcome that. Eric and Duncan won't!
埃里克和邓肯得有人劝退
Eric and Duncan must be persuaded to withdraw.
哦 你要找他们谈谈
Oh. You mean you'll have a word with them
我谈不了 我没看过档案
I can't. I haven't seen the files.
你呢 汉弗莱?      不行 大臣 这是党内事务
Humphrey, then. No, it's an internal party matter.
我插手不合适      那么 谁...
It would be most improper. Well, who...
你是说...?
You don't mean...?
我不行      没有别人行
I can't! No one else can.
你要我当面告诉同僚
You want me to tell one of my colleagues
他们一个是诈骗犯 一个是变态狂
he's a swindler and the other he's a pervert!
不必挑明 大臣 就说您不相信他们有错
Say you don't believe they've done anything wrong.
显示您掌握了情报就行
Just let them know you know something.
他们会叫我少管闲事
They'll tell me to mind my own business!
就说作为党主席
Then you say, as Chairman, it's your duty
您有责任透露信息给有关方面
to see the information reaches those who need to know.
党内执政者 主要捐助人
The Party Executive, major contributors,
元老 财团 皇室之类的
elder statesmen, patrons, the Palace, perhaps.
说清楚 他们别无选择 只能退出
Tell them they have no alternative but to pull out
力挺能保护他们的人
and support someone who will protect them.
你要我保护他们?
You want me to protect them?
他们的私事不影响国家安全 别人就无权干涉
It's nobody else's business as long as security's not involved.
我可做不来      您没选择 您都知道了
I don't have the stomach. You have no choice. you know.
别人不知道我知道 就当没这回事
Nobody else knows. Let's just forget all about it!
您真有魄力      魄力?为什么?
That would be very courageous. Courageous? Why?
如果将来出了事 爆出来您掩盖了内情
If later emerged you had the information and suppressed it
你要泄漏出去?      你徇私舞弊
You mean you'd leak it? Covering up for your chums...
"为救好友自毁前程 善莫大焉"(新约)
Greater love hath no man than should lay down his career.
汉弗莱 你威胁我
Humphrey, you're threatening me!
不 大臣 我在帮助您
No, Minister, I'm helping you.
你看 吉姆 首相还得有一项素质
You see there's one other quality Prime Ministers need.
杀手本能
The killer instinct.
对
Yes.
啊 谢谢
Ah, thanks.
敬10号      谢谢...我是说 好的
Well, here's to Number 10, eh? Thanks... I mean, yes.
什么事 吉姆?
What's up, Jim?
邓肯...
Duncan...
我有个问题      你不支持我了
...I have a problem. You're not going to support me.
对 不对      对 不对?
Yes. No. Yes, no?
正是
Exactly.
我得到一些信息
Some information has come my way.
哦 是吗?      重要信息
Oh, yes? Serious information.
关于你个人的...理财方式      你说什么?
Concerning your...financial operations. I beg your pardon?
大陆和通用公司的倒闭      运气不佳罢了
The collapse of Continental and General. just bad luck.
资金转移到董事长挂名的公司
The transfer of funds to directors' nominee companies.
没什么不妥当的      理论上是 不过...
There's nothing wrong with that. Technically, but...
联系到近海证券那起案子?
in conjunction with a similar case at Offshore Securities?
哪来的消息?      抱歉 可如果你要参选首相
Where did you get this? Sorry, if you're running for PM
我有责任把我知道的通报给党内元老
I shall share what I know with senior party members.
如果捅出去 国税局会展开调查 还有反欺诈局
there'd have to be an enquiry by Inland Revenue,Fraud Squad
当然那也没关系 你说全是光明正大的
None of that need matter if it's all above-board.
我相信 你说是就是 邓肯
And I'm sure it is, if you say so, Duncan.
没什么不合适      好 那我去告诉他们
There was nothing improper. Good, then I'm free to talk about it,
全都公布出来      且慢
bring it all out into the open. Hold on!
经济事务容易被曲解 人们会误会
Financial matters can be misinterpreted.
可不是
How true.
好吧 吉姆 我不一定非要进10号
Look, Jim, I'm not sure that I really want Number 10.
外交部也有很多好处 但我不会支持埃里克
Foreign Office is a better job. But I won't support Eric.
如果埃里克也选不上呢?
Suppose Eric didn't get it?
你愿不愿意转而支持另一个人?
How about transfer all your support to someone else?
谁?
Who?
这人必须赏识你的品质
It would have to be somebody who recognised your qualities,
想要你继续执掌外交部
who'd want you to stay at the Foreign Office.
知道小心对待大陆和通用公司
Someone who could be discreet about Continental and General.
你信得过的人
Someone you could trust.
一位老朋友
An old friend.
你说你自己?
Do you mean you?
我吗?我可没有这方面的野心
Me? I have absolutely no ambition in that direction.
还真是说你
You DO mean you!
我明白了      你知道这很严重吧 埃里克?
I see. You do realise this is serious, Eric?
是 你不打算帮我是吗?      是
Yes. And you're not going to help me, right? Yes.
帮还是不帮?      是
You are or you're not? Yes.
吉姆      我会帮你 但不是帮你竞选
Jim! I'm going to help you, but not to become PM.
你答应好的      那时我不知道阿根廷那位女士
You said you were. Until I heard about the lady from Argentina.
和其它人      明白了
And others. I see.
作为主席 我有我的职责
As Party Chairman I have my duty.
如果你当上首相 消息捅出去 全党都要遭殃
It'd be a disaster if you became PM and all this came out.
我可不想对女王陛下解释
I wouldn't care to have to explain it to Her Majesty.
你呢?
Would you?
我退出
I'll withdraw.
这非常明智
I think that's very sensible.
我们再不对任何人提这些事
So we'll say no more about it to anyone.
谢谢 吉姆
Thanks, Jim.
那邓肯要进10号了 老天爷      我可不允许
So Duncan will get Number 10. Not if I can help it.
那会是谁?      干杯
Who, then? Cheers.
你说你自己?      我吗?
You don't mean YOU? Me?
孩子长大了 安妮和我都想多花些时间在一起
Annie and I are hoping to spend more time together.
还真是说你
You DO mean you!
大臣      汉弗莱 什么事这么急?
Minister. Humphrey, what's the hurry?
真抱歉 我请了欧洲专使来开个小会
I've arranged a meeting with the European Commissioner.
莫里斯?他早上才坐飞机离开
Maurice? He flew out this morning.
他的航班延迟了      怎么?
His flight's been delayed. So?
也许能说服他为我们解决香肠问题
We might persuade him to solve our sausage problem.
汉弗莱 怎么解决?
How? (PHONE RINGS)
抱歉...喂?
Excuse me... Yes?
好的 请他进来 谢谢
Oh, yes, ask him to come in, will you? Thank you.
交给我办
Leave it to me.
只要...我让您帮腔就帮腔
Just, er, just give me support when I ask for it.
啊 莫里斯 幸会幸会      汉弗莱
Ah, Maurice, how nice to see you. Humphrey.
你们认识      吉姆 叫我来有何贵干?
You know each other. Jim, to what do I owe this pleasure?
大臣要我安排这次会面
The Minister asked me to arrange this meeting
请你帮忙解决个问题      问题
to see if you could help us with a problem. Problem.
当然
Of course.
问题是 欧共体在我国日渐不受欢迎
The problem is EEC is becoming unpopular over here.
对吧 大臣?      很不受欢迎
Isn't that so? Very unpopular.
你要重振它的声誉?      对
You want to restore its image? Yes.
不对      不对
No. No.
问题在于 大臣为了更多选票...
The Minister feels there would be more votes...
为了代表广大英国民众的意见
He would be better expressing the views of the British
他得与大家一道谴责欧共体 不能维护它
by joining the attack than leaping to its defence.
没错      但你们政府承诺支持我们
Exactly. But your party's committed to support us!
大臣的观点 据我所知
The Minister's point, as I understand it,
是政府支持它的概念和公约
is that the commitment is to the concept and the treaty.
公约      而不是支持这一机构
Treaty. It's not committed to the institutions,
也不支持其行动 或是个别政策
nor to the practices, nor to individual policies.
大臣曾向我提到一个例子 是吗 大臣?
The Minister was giving me an example the other day.
关于粮食生产      哦 对
About food production. Oh, yes.
我发现你们有个官员雇佣农民生产过剩粮食
One of your officials pays farmers to produce surplus food
隔壁又有个官员雇人销毁它们
while the next office pays people to destroy the surpluses.
没那事      没有?
That's not true! No?
绝不是隔壁 根本不在同一个楼层
It's not the next office, not even the same floor!
大臣还有几百个这种例子      几百个
The Minister has hundreds of similar examples. Hundreds.
问题在于 大臣觉得内阁里
The Minister is starting to think that a member of the Cabinet
应该有人告诉英国人民
ought to start telling the British people about them.
那怎么可以
But that would be intolerable!
意大利人都忍受不了
Even the Italians wouldn't stoop that low!
意大利人又不用管自家香肠叫"乳化高脂杂碎筒"
Italians aren't redesignate salami as high-fat offal tubing.
你们打算怎样?
And what are you proposing?
话说回来 要统一市场 也不能叫它香肠啊
we are committed to harmonisation. We cannot call it sausage.
你们有何建议?
What do you suggest?
政治是表述的艺术
Well, politics is about presentation.
为什么不叫它"英国肠"?
Why don't we call it "the British sausage"?
英国肠? Saucisse Anglaise(法语)
British sausage? Saucisse Anglaise.
Salsiccia Inglese(意语) Britisherwurst(德语)
Salsiccia Inglese. Britisherwurst.
对 我们可以...提请委员会批准
Yes, I think we could... recommend that to the Commission.
太好了
Splendid!
大臣一向认为欧共体是一家卓越的机构 对吧?
The Minister's always said the EEC is a splendid institution.
太卓越了
Splendid!
欧洲线记者到了      好的 都请进来
The European correspondents are here now. Good. Let 'em in.
不请进来吗?
Send them in.
要谈欧洲香肠问题吗?      是的 伯纳
This is about the Euro sausage problem? That's right, Bernard.
宣布您解决了?      不 伯纳
That you've solved it. No, Bernard.
解决问题不叫新闻 对媒体来说 噩耗才是喜讯
Solved problems aren't news. Bad news is good news.
我不会让他们无聊 我今天给他们一场灾难
I'm not give them a non-story. I'll give a disaster today
明天再来力挽狂澜      是这样啊
and a triumph tomorrow. I see.
早安 先生们      早安
Good morning, gentlemen! (ALL) Morning.
请坐 感谢大家前来
Do sit down. Good of you to come.
这件事还在协商中 没有定案
This is on a lobby basis, non-attributable.
但我们和欧共体有些分歧
We've got some trouble coming up with Brussels.
早晚有人会说 所以我不如主动通报出来
Somebody's going to tell you so I might as well tell you myself.
问题是 布鲁塞尔要宣布英国香肠非法
Brussels is about to make the British sausage illegal
不合欧共体条例      大臣
under EEC regulations. Minister...
不是香肠非法 只是名字
...not making the sausage illegal, just the name
谢谢 伯纳 我会提到的
Thank you, Bernard. I'll deal with that later.
什么叫"非法"?      不合法律规定
What do you mean, "illegal"? Effectively illegal.
猪肉肠必须含有75%瘦猪肉 牛肉肠也一样
pork sausage will contain 75% pork. The same for beef sausage.
也是75%瘦猪肉?
75% lean pork too?
75%瘦牛肉
75% lean beef.
将它们打入奢侈品范畴      什么时候会宣布?
make it a luxury food. When's this being promulgated?
大概下个月 眼下他们会否认
Next month, probably. They'll deny it
会说只不过改个名字
tell you they're just discussing changing its name.
政府打算怎么办?      我真不知道
What is the government going to do? I just don't know.
事态严重 我不想假装已经有了解决方案
It's a big problem. I won't pretend we've got an answer.
我还有别的事 有问题吗?
Well, I must rush. Any more questions?
什么时候能登报?      据我所知 明天吧
When can we use this? Tomorrow, as far as I'm concerned.
伯纳会请你们去宣传办喝一杯 谢谢光临
Bernard will give you a drink in the press office.
大臣 您知道媒体将发布假消息吧?
You realise the press will print something isn't true?
是吗?
Really?
真可怕
How frightful!
今天关于欧洲封杀英国香肠的消息
Today's story about the European ban on the British sausage
在政坛上引起轩然大波
has caused a maj'or political storm.
议会称香肠会成为又一块香蕉皮
Westminster say the sausage could be another banana skin.
为政府的稳步发展增添了新的考验
Adds to the government's problems with the succession
议员们不知所措 两大候选人
The two obvious candidates for the leadership
代表了党内两翼的极端
represent the extreme wings of the party.
不断有人施加压力 要求他们退出
Pressure is mounting for them to withdraw
另寻折衷的候选人
in favour of a compromise candidate.
但尚未有新竞争者出现在公众视野中
No other contender seems to have caught the public imagination.
体育方面      关掉吧 唐纳德
Now sport... Turn it off, Donald.
真的吗 折衷候选人的事?      恐怕是的
Is it true about the compromise candidate? I believe so.
他们哪来的消息?      我可猜不到 伯纳
Where DO they get their information? I can't imagine, Bernard!
反正我没说折衷 只说了缓和
Anyway, I never said compromise. I said moderate.
再说 大臣 为什么今晚BBC
Incidentally, why are BBC TV
和独立电视台要报导您的演讲?
and ITN covering your speech this evening?
我可不知道 伯纳
I can't imagine, Bernard.
我知道政府大楼防火保安措施很重要 可是...
I know fire policy in government is important but...
也许有人暗示我还要讲其它内容
Someone suggested I was going to raise other issues as well.
是谁?      我可猜不到 伯纳
Who? I can't imagine, Bernard.
我是个好欧洲人 我相信大欧洲理念
I am a good European. I believe in the European ideal.
两次世界大战的流血惨案决不能重演
Never again shall we repeat the bloodshed of the two world wars.
大欧洲永不会退缩
Europe is here to stay.
但我们同样不会屈从每项指令
we don't have to bow the knee to every directive
出自布鲁塞尔每个刚愎自用的小官僚
from every little bureaucratic Bonaparte in Brussels.
主权神圣不可侵犯
We are a sovereign nation still.
我们是英国人 我们为此自豪
We are British and proud of it!
我们已经太迁就那些欧洲农业政委
We made enough concessions to the Commissar for Agriculture.
我用政委这个词 并不是无心的
When I say Commissar, I use the word advisedly.
我们吞下了红酒湖和黄油山
We've swallowed the wine lake and the butter mountain,
眼看着法国朋友们打退英国卡车司机
we've watched our French friends beating up British drivers
禁止优质英国羊肉运到法国
carrying British lamb to the French.
我们已经卑躬屈膝 拱手而降
We have bowed and scraped, doffed our caps,
点头哈腰 顶礼膜拜 但我说 够了就是够了
Turned the other cheek, but I say enough is enough!
欧洲已经走得太远 他们威胁到了英国香肠
The Europeans are now threatening the British sausage.
他们明里说要标准化
They want to standardise it
暗里却在逼我们接受意大利和德国肠
they'll force us to eat salami and bratwurst
还有其它油腻的蒜味外国货
and other garlic-ridden greasy foods that are
与英式生活格格不入
totally alien to the British way of life.
你们早餐想吃意大利肠火腿蛋吗?
Do you want salami for breakfast with your egg and bacon?
我不想 我绝不同意
I don't! I won't!
他们把品脱转换成公升 英码转换成公尺
They've turned our pints into litres and our yards into metres.
我们放弃了六便士 三便士
We gave up the tanner, the threepenny bit
两先令和半克朗银币
the two-bob piece and the half crown,
但他们不能 也不会摧毁英国香肠
but they cannot and WILL not destroy the British sausage.
只要我还在这里
Not while I'm here!
正如马丁路德所说 "我立场如此 再无二话"
In the words of Martin Luther, here I stand. I can do no more.
很强硬啊 大臣     我强烈地感受到这些
Strong stuff, Minister. I feel strongly about it.
有时我怀疑你们做媒体的
I sometimes wonder whether you media people
能否体验我们其它人
realise how strongly we others feel
对英国 对我们祖国的强烈感受
about Britain, about our country.
我们爱它 为它而自豪
We love it and we're proud of it.
您不同意政府对欧共体的政策?
You're at odds with government policy over the EEC?
我很满意政府的政策 路德维克爵士
I'm very happy with government policy, Sir Ludovic.
政府可从未出台政策 封杀英国香肠
But it's never been policy to abolish the British sausage.
香肠不止好吃而已 它还营养丰富
Sausages are full of top-quality nourishment.
可是大臣 欧共体否认要封杀英国香肠
Brussels denies wanting to abolish the British sausage.
当然 他们知道阻力多大
They would. They know what they're up against
他们知道英国民意的力量
They know the strength of British opinion.
您的演讲被媒体广为传颂
Your speech got a lot of coverage and a lot of praise.
您是特意选择这一时机吗?      什么?
Was there any significance in the timing? Sorry?
贵党正在寻找新领导人 您的名字也略有提起
Your party is looking for leader, your name's been mentioned
哦 提的人还不少
Oh. Quite a lot, I believe.
可是没有 我从没有这方面的野心
But no, I've no ambitions at all in that direction.
那您肯定不会参选了?
So you definitely won't let your name go forward?
这个嘛 阿路...我向来...
Well, Ludo... All I've...
我向来以造福国家为己任 从不在乎岗位
All I wanted to do is serve my country, never sought office.
但如果同僚们说服我
But if my colleagues persuaded me
进入10号才最能造福国家
the best place to serve it from was 10 Downing Street,
我也只能勉为其难 担起责任来
I reluctantly be persuaded to undertake the responsibility
完全舍弃我的私心
whatever my own private wishes might be.
既然不参选 您会投票给谁?
If you're not in the running, who will you vote for?
现在还为时过早 但我要说
Well, it's far too early to say. But I will say this.
这是治愈的时代
This is a time for healing.
时代要求我们着眼于共识 求同存异
A time to stress what we agree about
要看到对手好的一面 不能一味挑错
We should be looking for the good in our opponents
你知道 人人皆有优点 阿路
There's good in everyone, you know, Ludo.
除了法国人      除了...
Except the French! Except...
甚至包括法国人
Even the French.
大臣 您在内阁的时候议会传来消息
A message came from House while you were in committee.
怎么?
Yes?
他们把党员大会提前了
They brought the party meeting forward.
一小时前就开始了      提前了?
Brought it forward?
他们随时会决定是否再提出一人与您对垒
They'll decide if they're going to bring up another candidate
出决议了组织秘书会打电话来
The Chief Whip will phone as soon as it's over.
他会不会...他们...要是...
W-W-Will he... W-What will they... What if...
哪个电话?
Which phone?
什么?      他会打哪个电话?
What? Which phone will he ring on?
哦 大概是这个
Oh. Er, this one, probably.
或者这个
Or this one.
都可能 真的
Either, really.
就算邓肯和埃里克真的退出
If Duncan and Eric withdraw, which they will,
他们也不一定支持我
they might not support me.
那就要普选了
That means an election.
没错 可您是双方最看好的候选人
You're the favourite candidate for both sides,
不会反对您的      他们是这么说
so you'll be unopposed. That's what they say.
算了 急也没用
Oh, well... No point in worrying about it.
还是坐下歇歇气
Might as well sit down and relax. (PHONE RINGS)
喂?
Yes?
好的
Yes.
伯纳有急事找您
Bernard has an urgent message.
大臣 王宫打来电话
Minister, the Palace have been on the phone.
王宫?干吗?      问您5点能否觐见女王
Will you be free to kiss hands at five o'clock?
如果没有第二名候选人的话
In the event of an unopposed recommendation.
这个 我...
Well, I...
我想应该没问题
I think I might be able to make that.
伯纳
Bernard...
如果...要是我...
Supposing... You know if I...
我还得要个首席私人秘书
I'd still want a Principal Private Secretary.
你觉得你...      哦 大臣
Do you think, er... Oh, Minister.
天呐
Gosh!
可以的吧 汉弗莱?      这个
That'll be all right, won't it, Humphrey? Well...
首相的话就是法律 大臣
The Prime Minister's word is law.
喂?
Yes?
好的
Yes.
对 他在这里
Yes, he's here.
我会转告他
I'll tell him.
是...不是...是不是...
It... It... It... Is...
是不是我?
Is it me?
是 首相
Yes, Prime Minister!
"是,大臣" 全剧终 感谢大家的支持 我们唐宁街十号再会!